Guide to the C.C. Spaulding Papers, 1889-1990 RL.01241
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
C.C. Spaulding papers
1889-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Spaulding, C. C. (Charles Clinton), 1874-1952
RL.01241
25 Linear Feet 18750 items
President of North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1923-1952. NC Mutual is the oldest currently active African American-owned insurance company in the United States, founded in 1898 and headquartered in Durham, North Carolina. The collection contains photographs, miscellaneous business papers, programs, speeches, clippings related to C. C. Spaulding, black civil rights, and to African American life more generally, in addition to administrative materials and various publications created by and related to North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company. These papers document the growth of North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company in the mid-twentieth century, Spaulding's and the company's connection to the community, and their involvement in African American issues (local and beyond) and livelihood. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, except the Photography Series is CLOSED pending processing.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The C.C. Spaulding Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999.
Biographical Note
Charles Clinton Spaulding was born near Clarkton, N.C., on August 1, 1874, the son of ex-slaves. He began working with Dr. A.M. Moore and John Merrick in Durham, N.C., in 1898 as the first employee of the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company. In 1899, C.C. Spaulding became the general manager of NC Mutual, gradually rising to the rank of president in 1923. He remained president until his death in 1952. His cousin, Asa T. Spaulding, later assumed the presidency of NC Mutual.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of a variety of materials, only some of which date from the lifetime of C.C. Spaulding. Many of the materials date from the mid-1950s through the 1970s, suggesting that the papers were collected and transferred to Duke without explicit sorting to distinguish C.C. Spaulding's files from other NC Mutual materials. Essentially, this collection serves as the forerunner to the NC Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, also held at Duke University's Rubenstein Library. Researchers interested in the company's history should consult both collections.
The C.C. Spaulding Papers are arranged into the following series: Clippings, NC Mutual, Writings/Speeches, Subjects, Personal/Family, and Photographs. The Photography Series (2 boxes) is currently closed to researchers, pending processing.
The Clippings Series is the largest series within the collection, and consists of newspaper and magazine clippings collected by various people, including C.C. Spaulding, between the 1920s and the 1970s. The majority of these materials have been photocopied onto acid-free paper, with the original newspaper discarded. Clippings have been arranged alphabetically by subject or name. Major topics present in the series include the civil rights movement, segregation/integration, and African American education, and community life; insurance, business, and financial news; press coverage of C.C. Spaulding's activities and appearances; and press coverage of the NC Mutual Company. This series also includes some scrapbooks of oversize clippings covering miscellaneous topics.
The NC Mutual Series consists of several subseries: Finances, Committees, Publicity/Events, Research/Reports, Publications/Printed Materials, and Correspondence. The Finances Subseries includes the company's annual earnings statements, controller reports, and actuarial files. Within the Committees Subseries is a substantial amount of information from the Company History Committee, which published The NC Mutual Story in 1971. Another major initiative documented within the NC Mutual Series is the opening of the 1966 NC Mutual office building, one of the tallest buildings in downtown Durham. Files relating to the groundbreaking, dedication, and programming surrounding the building's opening are held in the Publicity/Events Subseries. Publicity/Events also includes advertisements and materials from the launching of the SS John Merrick during World War II. Other notable materials held in the NC Mutual Series are some of C.C. Spaulding's correspondence as company president, issues of various publications produced by NC Mutual, and research materials commissioned by the company on issues such as real estate, director's fees, and workmen's compensation.
The Subjects Series contains files arranged by topic which loosely relate to the interests of NC Mutual and its management, including life insurance, "The Negro," and North Carolina. This series is related to the Clippings Series but largely consists of printed materials and other writings or publications collected by unknown parties.
The Writings/Speeches Series includes drafts, essays, articles, and speeches written by C.C. Spaulding, Asa T. Spaulding, and W.J. Kennedy, Jr. Within C.C. Spaulding's materials are writings and speeches delivered in his capacity as NC Mutual president. Other writings include articles, letters to the editor, and commencement or other public addresses.
The Personal/Family Series includes death and memorial materials for A.M. Moore and C.C. Spaulding, two NC Mutual presidents, as well as commemorations, honors, and other materials documenting the men's public service in the twentieth century. Other items in this series include financial materials from John and Martha Merrick, some anonymous volumes, and some materials relating to Asa Spaulding.
Related Material
This collection includes extensive information about NC Mutual. For more information about that company, please consult the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives. More information about Asa Spaulding, a later president of NC Mutual, can be found in the Asa and Elna Spaulding Papers. Both collections are held by the Rubenstein Library. (NC Mutual's Archive is jointly held between Duke and NC Central University.)
Insurance companies, American -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Social conditions; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History -- 20th century; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Clippings (information artifacts); Spaulding, Asa T. (Asa Timothy), 1902-1990; Spaulding, C. C. (Charles Clinton), 1874-1952; Moore, A. M. (Aaron McDuffie), 1863-1923; North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company; Spaulding family
- Clippings, 1910s-1980s, 10 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The majority of this series consists of newspaper clippings originally collected by C.C. Spaulding, Asa Spaulding, and other unknown figures. Only a small amount of original newspapers and magazine pages remain in the series; nearly all of the clippings are photocopies of the original article. Many of the clippings relate to the civil rights movement, post-dating C.C. Spaulding's life, suggesting that they were acquired by other people associated with NC Mutual in the mid-twentieth century. Topics include the desegregation/integration of schools and public spaces; racial violence, lawsuits, and protests accompanying the civil rights movement; African American education, colleges, and businesses; politics; issues relating to the Cold War; insurance companies and governance; and other miscellaneous files on various public figures and events. NC Mutual coverage and publicity represents another significant component of the series, along with a large amount of clippings documenting C.C. Spaulding's speeches, appearances, and work with NC Mutual. The bulk of the clippings date from the 1940s through the 1960s.
  - African American education/school suits, 1930s-1960s, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - African American history (Box 1)
  - African American soldiers (Box 1)
  - Black Muslims (Box 1)
  - Celebrities/Entertainers/Heroes (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights movement, 1940s-1953, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights movement, 1954-1963, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights movement--Birmingham, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights movement--March on Washington, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Cold War/USSR (Box 2)
  - Community/Civic Clubs/Fraternities/Sororities (Box 2)
  - Democratic Party (Box 2)
  - Fultz Quadruplets, Reidsville, NC, 1946-1950s (Box 2)
  - Girl Friends, Inc., 1950s (Box 2)
  - Girl Scouts, 1930s-1950s (Box 2)
  - Goodloe, J.W., 1950s (Box 2)
  - Government regulations/Consumers/Insurance (Box 2)
  - Graham, Franklin P. (Box 2)
  - "Green Pastures" (Box 2)
  - Haiti, 1949-1950s (Box 2)
  - Hampton Inst., Hampton, Va. (Box 2)
  - Hansberry, William 60 (Box 2)
  - Hastie, William H. (Box 2)
  - Hatcher, A. T. (Associate Press Sea) (Box 2)
  - Health, 1930s-1950s (Box 3)
  - Health Bulletins, 1935-1940s (Box 3)
  - Hemingway, "The Dangerous Summer" (Box 3)
  - Henderson, J. J. (Box 3)
  - Heritage of Splendor (Box 3)
  - Higher Education (Box 3)
  - Hill, John Sprunt (Box 3)
  - Hill, William D. (Box 3)
  - Hippocratic Oath (Box 3)
  - Historically Black Colleges/Technical Schools (Box 3)
  - Hobbies (Box 3)
  - Holidays (Box 3)
  - Holidays--Christmas (Box 3)
  - Holidays--Easter (Box 3)
  - Holy land (Box 3)
  - Homes in the South (Box 3)
  - Hospitals (Negro) (Box 3)
  - Hospitalization (Box 3)
  - Housing/Rent, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Housewives League (Box 3)
  - Howard University, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Hughes, Langston (Box 3)
  - Human Relations (Box 3)
  - Human Rights (Box 3)
  - Income (Box 3)
  - India and personalities (Box 3)
  - Industrial Life Insurance Co. (Box 3)
  - Insurance, 1960s, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Insurance Companies (Box 4)
  - Insurance Index (Box 4)
  - Insurance 50 years progress (Box 4)
  - Integration (Box 4)
  - Jobs (Box 4)
  - Merrick, E.R. (Box 4)
  - Merrick, John (includes USS John Merrick), 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Life Insurance companies/Banks/Mutual companies (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous national/international news coverage, 1960s, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Moore, A.M. (Box 4)
  - Moore, A.M. (clippings collected by him) (Box 4)
  - Morehouse College, Atlanta (Box 4)
  - Mothers Day/Mother of the Year (Box 4)
  - Movies/Television (Box 4)
  - Mutual Life Insurance of New York (Box 4)
  - Mutual Savings and Loan Assoc., Durham, NC (Box 4)
  - National Baptist Convention (Box 4)
  - "Nation's Business" photocopies, 1948-1950 (Box 4)
  - National Alliance of Postal Employees (NAPE), 1950s (Box 4)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1940s-1950s, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1940s-1950s, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - National Association of College Women (Box 5)
  - National Association of Colored Women (Box 5)
  - National Business Educational League, 1930s (Box 5)
  - National Council of Catholic Men (Box 5)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ (U.S.) (Box 5)
  - National Council of Negro Women (Box 5)
  - National Dental Association (Box 5)
  - National Foundation for Brotherhood (Box 5)
  - National Medical Association/American Medical Association, 1950s (Box 5)
  - National Negro Business League, 1920s-1950s (Box 5)
  - National Negro Finance Corporation, 1920s-1940s (Box 5)
  - National Negro Insurance Association, 1934 (Box 5)
  - National Negro Insurance Association, 1935-1959, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Native Americans (Box 5)
  - Negro Hospitals, 1940s-1950s (Box 5)
  - Negro Hotels,1940s-1950s (Box 5)
  - Negro in entertainment (Box 5)
  - Negro Press, 1950s (Box 5)
  - North Carolina College (NC College), 1940s-1960s (Box 5)
  - North Carolina College (NC College), 1940s-1960s, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Mutual (NC Mutual) coverage, 1940s-1960s, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Mutual (NC Mutual) coverage, 1960s-1970s, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Nuclear testing, 1960s (Box 6)
  - Nursing (Box 6)
  - Opera (Box 13)
  - Police/FBI agents, 1940s-1950s (Box 13)
  - Polio/Infantile paralysis (Box 13)
  - Population statistics (Box 13)
  - Prisons/Prisoners (Box 13)
  - Progressive Party (Box 13)
  - Pulitzer/Nobel Prize, 1949-1960s (Box 13)
  - Race relations, 1940s-1950s (Box 13)
  - Racial violence/Lynching (Box 13)
  - Recreation (Box 13)
  - Religion/Churches (Box 13)
  - Robeson, Paul (Box 13)
  - Robinson, Jackie (Box 13)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1940s-1960s (Box 13)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 13)
  - Rowan, Carl, 1960s (Box 13)
  - Sampson, Edith (Box 13)
  - Sanford, Terry, 1961 (Box 13)
  - Scarborough Nursery (Box 13)
  - Science/Scientists, 1960s (Box 13)
  - Segregation, 1940s-1960s, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Segregation, 1940s-1960s, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Shaw University (Box 14)
  - Shepard, James E., 1940s-1950s (Box 14)
  - Soap Box Derby, 1940s-1950s (Box 14)
  - Social Security (Box 14)
  - Southern Aid Society, 1930s (Box 14)
  - Space Race (Box 14)
  - Spaulding, Asa (Box 14)
  - Spaulding, C.C., publicity/coverage, 1920s-1952 and undated, 18 folders (Box 14)
  - Spaulding family (Box 14)
  - "Statistics About the Negro," 1932-1970, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Supreme Court, 1950s (Box 14)
  - Supreme Liberty Life Insurance, Chicago, 1950s (Box 14)
  - Switzerland (Box 14)
  - Teachers (Box 14)
  - Thanksgiving (Box 14)
  - Travel (Box 14)
  - United Kingdom (Box 14)
  - United Nations (Box 14)
  - U.S. Navy (Box 14)
  - Women (Box 14)
  - Oversized miscellaneous clippings (Box 15)
  - Oversized scrapbooks of miscellaneous clippings (Box 16)
  - Oversized scrapbooks of miscellaneous clippings (Box 17)
- NC Mutual, 1910s-1990s, 4 boxes
  The NC Mutual Series consists of several subseries: Finances, Committees, Publicity/Events, Research/Reports, Publications/Printed Materials, and Correspondence. The Finances Subseries includes the company's annual earnings statements, controller reports, and actuarial files. Within the Committees Subseries is a substantial amount of information from the Company History Committee, which published The NC Mutual Story in 1971. Another major initiative documented within the NC Mutual Series is the opening of the 1966 NC Mutual office building, one of the tallest buildings in downtown Durham. Files relating to the groundbreaking, dedication, and programming surrounding the building's opening are held in the Publicity/Events Subseries. Publicity/Events also includes advertisements and materials from the launching of the SS John Merrick during World War II. Other notable materials held in the NC Mutual Series are some of C.C. Spaulding's correspondence as company president, issues of various publications produced by NC Mutual, and research materials commissioned by the company on issues such as real estate, director's fees, and workmen's compensation.
  - Finances (Box 7)
    - Financial Bulletins: Tennessee, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
    - Financial Bulletins: Georgia, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
    - Financial Bulletins: Mississippi, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
    - Financial Bulletins: South Carolina, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
    - Financial Bulletins: Alabama, Florida, Arkansas, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
    - Financial Bulletins: E. North Carolina and Virginia, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
    - Solvent Savings Company receipts and statements, 1930s-1950s (Box 7)
    - Paid-up endowments, 1948 (Box 7)
    - Earnings statements, advertising, 1930s-1950s, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Actuary and Controller annual reports, 1938-1961, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Actuarial staff meeting minutes, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Annual reports (drafts), 1930s (Box 7)
    - Annual statements, 1940s-1960s (Box 7)
  - Committees (Box 7)
    - Home Office Committee meeting minutes, 1930-1957, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Securities Investment Committee minutes, 1950-1952 (Box 7)
    - Standing committees, Durham office, 1953 (Box 7)
    - Board meetings/Executive Committee meetings, 1960-1965, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with other companies re: 50th Anniversary, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Golden Anniversary Planning Committee, 1949 (Box 7)
    - Company History Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
    - Company History Committee, 1967-1971, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Company History Committee: NC Mutual Story publication, 1970-1972, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Staff training (Box 8)
  - Publicity/Events (Box 8)
    - Questionnaires/Biographical Sketches, 1940s-1960s (Box 8)
    - Press releases, 1940s-1950s and 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Launching of S.S. John Merrick, 1942-1943 (Box 8)
    - Advertising/Public Relations, 1950s-1960s (Box 8)
    - Advertisements/Marketing drafts (Box 8)
    - Awards (Box 8)
    - Merrick-Moore Scholarship Fund (Box 8)
    - Press Kit materials, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
    - New Building, 1963-1966, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - New Building, 1963-1966, 7 folders (Box 9)
  - Reports/Research (Box 9)
    - Workmen's Compensation studies/research, 1970s (Box 9)
    - Insurance companies studies/research, 1960s-1970s (Box 9)
    - Director's Fees surveys, 1970s (Box 9)
    - Real estate studies, 1960s-1970s (Box 9)
    - Real Estate Dept. reports, 1930s-1940s (Box 9)
    - Reports on Examinations, 1920s-1940s, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Publications/Printed Materials (Box 9)
    - Sample insurance policies (largely blank), 1910s-1950s and undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Publication logistics: printing, proofs, etc., 1950s (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous publications by NC Mutual (Box 9)
    - NC Mutual Forum programs and guidelines, 1942-1954 (Box 9)
    - Company history publications, 1920s-1960s (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous programs, bulletins, etc., 1960s, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - The Whetstone: nominations for women's issue, 1944 (Box 10)
    - The Whetstone: entries/poems submitted/used, 1930s-1960s (Box 10)
    - The Whetstone: various issues, 1950s-1970s, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - The Mutual publication, 1920s (Box 10)
    - Negro Progress publications, 1950s-1960s (Box 10)
    - The Weekly Review, Vol. 33, 1957, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Correspondence to/from C.C. Spaulding while abroad, 1931-1932 (Box 10)
    - C.C. Spaulding's Christmas/Thanksgiving messages, 1920s-1940s (Box 10)
    - C.C. Spaulding's correspondence re: Jim Crow and Civil Rights, 1930s-1940s (Box 10)
    - C.C. Spaulding's correspondence re: NC Mutual, 1930s-1951, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - W.D. Hill correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence re: NC Mutual expansion into Pennsylvania, 1938 (Box 10)
    - Victor S. Bryant correspondence, 1949-1952 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence re: C.C. Spaulding's death, 1952-1953 (Box 10)
    - C.C. Spaulding, Jr.'s correspondence, 1960s (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1960s-1970s, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Subjects/Research, 1920s-1970s, 1 boxes
  The Subjects/Research Series contains files arranged by topic which loosely relate to the interests of NC Mutual and its management, including life insurance, "The Negro," and North Carolina. This series is related to the Clippings Series but largely consists of printed materials and other writings or publications collected by unknown parties.
  - 18th Amendment (Box 11)
  - G.W. Cox Jr. IBM and Burroughs Proposals (Box 11)
  - Insurance anti-trust lawsuit, 1944 (Box 11)
  - Insurance bulletins (US Chamber of Commerce) (Box 11)
  - Insurance company rankings, 1928-1942 (Box 11)
  - Insurance Research and Review Service reports (Box 11)
  - Insurance statistics (Box 11)
  - Life insurance (Box 11)
  - The Negro, 1930s-1960s, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Negro businesses (Box 11)
  - North Carolina (Box 11)
  - Race relations, 1 folders (Box 11)
  - Shaw University (Box 11)
- Writings/Speeches, 1920s-1970s, 1 boxes
  The Writings/Speeches Series includes drafts, essays, articles, and speeches written by C.C. Spaulding, Asa T. Spaulding, and W.J. Kennedy, Jr. Within C.C. Spaulding's materials are writings and speeches delivered in his capacity as NC Mutual president. Other writings include articles, letters to the editor, and commencement or other public addresses.
  - Essays/speeches by C.C. Spaulding, 1920s-1940s and undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - NC Mutual writings by C.C. Spaulding, 1920s-1940s (Box 12)
  - Photocopied newspaper columns by C.C. Spaulding (Box 12)
  - Essays/articles/speeches by Asa T. Spaulding (Box 12)
  - "Transformation of a Cargo," draft by W.J. Kennedy, Jr., 1966 (Box 12)
- Personal/Family Materials, 1889-1970s, 1 boxes
  The Personal/Family Series includes death and memorial materials for A.M. Moore and C.C. Spaulding, as well as commemorations, honors, and other materials documenting the men's public service in the twentieth century. Other items in this series include financial materials from John and Martha Merrick, some anonymous volumes, and some materials relating to Asa Spaulding.
  - Anonymous memo book, 1889 (Box 12)
  - E.R. Merrick financial statements, 1930s (Box 12)
  - Martha Merrick financial statements, 1930s, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - A.M. Moore correspondence, undated (Box 12)
  - A.M. Moore funeral/obituaries, 1923 (Box 12)
  - A.M. Moore's NC Negro education materials (miscellaneous), 1910s-1920s (Box 12)
  - C.C. Spaulding's awards and honors (Box 12)
  - Essays and articles honoring C.C. Spaulding, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Sympathy cards/telegrams/memorials re: C.C. Spaulding's death, 1952-1960s, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Asa T. Spaulding biographical sketches, 1956-1960s (Box 12)
  - Anonymous monthly planner, 1966 (Box 12)
  - White Rock Baptist Church (Box 12)
- Photographs, 1910s-1970s, 2 boxes
  This series includes NC Mutual publicity photographs as well as personal photographs from A.M. Moore and the Spaulding family.
  - Aaron McDuffie Moore (Box 18)
  - A.M. Moore House- Shaw University (Box 18)
  - Asa T. Spaulding, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - C.C. Spaulding Group photos (Box 18)
  - C.C. Spaulding miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Dedication and Ground Breaking Ceremony, 1966 (Box 18)
  - District Offices (Box 18)
  - Funeral- C.C. Spaulding, 1952 (Box 18)
  - A.M. Moore Haitian Missionaries, 1920s (Box 18)
  - Haiti Trip- C.C. Spaulding (Box 18)
  - Merrick Grave (Box 18)
  - Miscellaenous, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - National Negro Insurance Association (Box 18)
  - NCM Story, 1909-1961 (Box 18)
  - NC Mutual (Box 18)
  - NC Mutual "Managers" (Box 18)
  - NC Mutual print block (Box 18)
  - NC Mutual staff, 1960s; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Oversize photographs and posters, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Patricia Spaulding, Elna Spaulding, and children (Box 18)
  - Portraits (Box 18)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains a portrait of Martha Merrick Donnell, daughter of John Merrick
  - Second Quarter, 1965 (Box 18)
  - Trips- Asa T. Spaulding (Box 18)
  - Hospital Care Association reel (Box 18)
  - C.C. Spaulding Anniversary and Awards (Box 18)